"How Effective Are Statins?"
In my video on how doctors
paternalistically
mislead patients
about statin risks and benefits
for their own good,
I talk about how,
for the majority
of patients surveyed,
the expectation of benefit
from drugs like statins
is higher than the actual
benefit the drugs provide;
so, this creates tension
between a patient’s
right to know
and the likely reduction
in the chance
they’d agree to take it
if they knew
how little benefit
the drug offered.
On a population scale,
that would be devastating.
For example,
statins probably prevent
tens of thousands of deaths
a year in the United States.
However, if patients were
routinely told the truth,
as many as 75% of patients
might stop treatment.
So, unless we keep everyone
in the dark,
30,000 people could die.
So, what should doctors do?
I agree with these doctors
that we have to tell the truth
even if it means
the patient doesn’t take it
and potentially dies
as a result.
It’s their body, their choice.
Of course, I wish
this fully-informed consent
would extend to telling people
about the beneficial role
of a healthy diet,
but before we get into that,
let’s answer
the statins question.
Are they worth it?
Maybe you’re in the 25%
of people
who would still take it,
even knowing the whole truth.
So, what is the whole truth?
We’ve all seen the drug ads,
like this one touting
atorvastatin, Lipitor,
as reducing the risk
of a heart attack
by about a third.
But as you can see
in the small print,
"That means
in a large clinical study,
three percent of patients
taking a sugar pill
had a heart attack
compared to 2% of patients
taking Lipitor."
Going from three to two
is indeed a drop
by a third in relative risk,
but the drop in absolute risk
was only 1%,
which sounds less impressive.
This is common
even in the medical literature-
no surprise,
since journal articles
are often written
by drug manufacturers.
Now, the 3% to 2% Lipitor drop
was over a period
of only about three years.
These drugs are to be taken
over a lifetime;
so, the benefits accrue.
Over four or five years,
the absolute risk reduction
might reach 1.3%,
but you can see why
many patients
are not very moved.
Even in the studies
where people were presented
with an idealized tablet
with no side effects,
more than a third stated
that they would not consider
taking a medication
that would drop
their five-year absolute risk
by 5% or more.
Only about 50% of people
would consider
taking preventive medications
that prolonged their life
by less than eight months.
The average expected
longevity benefit from statins
ranges from a few months
to a few years
depending on risk.
In this patient population here,
the expected lifespan gain
would be about a year,
whereas here’s the distribution
of what people would want
to take a drug every day
for the rest of their lives.
About a third said,
"Three months?
I’ll take it."
Whereas about 1 in 10 said
they wouldn’t take pills
even if they got to live
an extra ten years or more.
That’s why
it’s such a personal decision,
because we are
all over the place
in terms of what
we’re willing to accept.
Your doctor may not care,
though.
Physicians were presented
with the case of a man
with a 7% to 10% risk of dying
from cardiovascular disease
over the next decade
who explicitly told the doctor
that they only want
to take a statin
if it would increase
their lifespan
by a certain amount.
Some doctors were told
the patient demanded
at least eight years of life,
and others were told
the patient only asked
for a matter of months,
which is actually
what they’d gain in real life;
yet, 83% of the doctors said
they’d prescribe it
to the patients
who unrealistically demanded
eight years,
which is almost exactly
the same percentage
recommended by the doctors
who were told
the patient only wanted
a few months.
In other words,
the doctors were insensitive
to patient preferences
regarding survival gain.
Now, for primary prevention,
trying to prevent
your first heart attack,
no overall survival benefits
have been found.
Indeed, only one
of eight studies
showed that statins actually
made people live longer,
but presumably
that’s because the studies
only lasted a few years,
and for low-risk populations,
the risk of dying
from cardiovascular disease
in that time may just be
a few percent anyway.
But such trials do show
fewer events,
heart attacks and strokes;
so, on a public health scale,
it would make sense
not to just wait for people
to have a heart attack
before starting them
on cholesterol-lowering drugs.
Critics counter that, yes,
that sounds good,
and if statins had
these benefits
without side effects,
then perhaps the decision
to start them is understandable,
but look, because statins
increase our risk of diabetes,
these drugs might give
as many people diabetes
as it does prevent them
from having a heart attack
or stroke.
But the stat they cite
is from a combination
of primary and secondary
prevention trials.
In primary prevention trials,
like trying to prevent
your first heart attack,
there is no increased
diabetes risk.
You only see that
in secondary prevention trials
where people are trying
to prevent
their second heart attack,
for instance.
This might be
because their risk of diabetes
is higher in general,
or they’re using
higher doses of statins.
Intensive-dose statin therapy
is associated with a greater
increased risk
of new-onset diabetes
compared to moderate-dose
statin therapy.
Of course, intensive therapy
also offers more benefits
in terms of cardiovascular
protection.
Then, if you separate out
the primary prevention trials
by the populations
who have low or high rates
of diabetes
regardless of the drug,
statins only seem
to increase risk among those
with high baseline rates.
Again, this could be
a consequence of running
shorter-term trials
in low-risk populations.
The big benefits,
preventing death,
may not show up,
but the big downside,
like the drug
giving you diabetes,
may also not show up.
But even in the trials that
do show increased diabetes,
the risk of getting diabetes
may be vastly offset
by the cardiovascular protection
offered from statin therapy.
Of course, a healthy diet
may reduce the risk of both
at the same time,
but sticking with
the drug discussion
before moving on to diet,
increased diabetes risk
is not the only side effect
of statins.
What about risks to our muscles,
liver, kidney, and brain?
I’ll get into
all of those, next.